welcome back to 5-minute fifth everyone
dr. aunty Galpin here probably the most
common question I've ever got in my
career is Andy how do I get stronger
without getting bigger this is important
for people who are in say weight base
class sports or for anyone who for
whatever reason just decides they want
to get stronger but don't want to add
any muscle mass well we have a two-part
answer that but the first direct most
direct answer is of course you can we've
seen this routinely across many sports
and this is how people who are in say
sports like weightlifting where they
have weight classes they can continue to
get stronger without adding any more
muscle and still staying in their weight
class and so the answer is really two
parts here we have to talk about the
programming because the type of lifting
you do influences whether you get
strength or high purchase for your both
and then we'll talk about the underlying
physiology very very quickly so we'll
start off with the program design stuff
now what you're going to see here and
one hand car one of these columns is the
concepts and as the famous saying goes
the concepts are a few but the methods
are many and so I'll give you the
fundamental concepts and as long as in
your training you hit these ideas you
should be able to add significant
strength without adding too much muscle
mass the methods I'll just give you a
few but those are infinite and you're
gonna have to see other videos and use
your logic to figure it out from there
but first and foremost we typically use
complex movements we don't need the
isolate muscle groups or small joints or
single muscle movements here you can but
you don't need to in terms of the volume
we want to do a small repetitions per
set prescription something like 1 to 5
reps and this is based on the common law
of specificity or the said principle so
that the specific adaptations to impose
demands you want to get better shooting
a free throw the best thing you could
ever do shoot a free throw you want to
get better at being strong the best
thing you could ever do is pick
something up that's very very very very
heavy alright but you don't want to do a
tremendous amount of sets for that and
so you see that 3 to 20 ish wind that
was large because it depends on a lot of
things how many other movements you're
doing how many days you're lifting this
week how advanced you are so a beginner
maybe wants to stay it maybe 3 or 4 sets
maybe in meter mediate and love to do
something I'm more like 5 sets of 5 and
an advanced person might be doing
something
like 10 or 15 or even 20 sets of two
reps well you notice in any of those
scenarios you're still never doing more
than four there are five reps maybe six
at the most per set because you want the
quality behind so if you want to avoid a
ton of hypertrophy these low volume high
intensity by high intensity mean
percentage or one or at max these
schemes tend to induce a lot of strength
without a ton of hypertrophy you're
gonna get some your lifting but it won't
be nearly as much so as long as you do
this and then you control your calories
you should have no problem getting
stronger for a long time without adding
a significant amount of muscle mass so
like I said it's got to be 80 to 100
percent any runner at max got to be
heavy all right no doubt about that if
you're wondering how you can get plus
100 you're gonna have to watch some of
my other videos you want to try to go
fast even though we know from the force
velocity care if you're not going to go
very fast but that's okay you're still
trying to move quickly most the time and
then like that quality thing we talked
about you're gonna want to use the most
amount of rests possible percent so a
couple of minutes or Maxima whatever
that be in terms of the methods you got
a lot of options here push pulls carries
your classic hinges presses squats all
that stuff is very very good for a
general strength but don't forget the
negatives in the east eccentric work
very good to really slow controlled
stuff is highly effective for strength
ah be careful the doms though with the
eccentric isometric they're also very
good let's not forget these things
particularly for the connective tissue
in the joints I recommend checking out
Cal Dietz and his triphasic system for
this he's got a very good approach to
integrating those three movement
patterns any weight lifting movement so
this would be the sport of weightlifting
so snatches clean and jerks pulls stuff
like that but then again also some other
stuff from the powerlifting world like
dynamic variable resistance or
accommodating resistance or compensatory
acceleration all that's kind of the same
thing bands and chains heavy bands and
chains I should say rather you can look
on the 55 minute version of this video
I'm going to that stuff in depth same
thing with cluster sets another way to
vary how you execute the volume
intensity that are very effective for
strength in terms of the physiology
though that's the other side of the
equation what's really happening is a
whole bunch of stuff and I'm gonna go
through this very quickly you're gonna
have to watch the extended version for
more but you have a whole host of
adaptations from the nervous system and
so if you watch one of my other videos
which is how you contract and how you
produce force quickly I go over all the
different aspects well you can see from
any physiology textbook or Wikipedia and
you can go through the nerve stuff and
look at all the different adaptations
but effectively what happens is you
become more efficient and better at
activating the nervous system that then
contracts on muscle that causes
connective tissue to pull on bone and
makes you move so anything in that
system the sliding filament theory if
you've had X for this class any of that
stuff improves and adapts to strength
training again this is where it's
slightly different from hypertrophy work
and so you're able to produce more force
without having to have any bigger of a
muscle but number two three and four
where people tend to forget and so let's
not forget there are a whole host of
cellular adaptations you can get
everything from the sarcoplasmic
reticulum to calcium sensitivity to
affinity to the actin and myosin all of
these things improve the ability of the
muscle to contract and so you can see
there's is to be that contract on
velocity so independent of changing the
size of a fiber the fiber can learn to
develop more force or velocity without
getting any bigger since force is mass
times acceleration and power is force
times velocity if you're getting faster
if you're produced producing with more
force per area this is strength without
getting bigger you can also change your
fiber types so we have the significant
evidence to suggest slow touch fibers
can convert to fast rich fibers this in
and of itself won't change fiber science
per se no bigger but you will produce
more force or velocity and then also a
pan-asian angle so the angle at which
your muscle goes into your tear tendon
and connective tissue or in the bone can
change and if it goes one way at Favors
speed the range of motion if it goes the
other way at Favors force production so
this all those things from the muscle
side allow you to produce more for
stopping bigger connective tissue well
this is the Forgotten child we don't
have a ton of data on this but let's not
forget that we can improve efficiency
there and even connective properties
from that and then the last one will be
biomechanical so changes in mechanical
advantage is good but your tech
Niq this is could be your setup or your
position or it could be something like
an increase in muscle size somewhere
else and decrease in another one that
changed in mechanical advantage so all
that comes together that helps you allow
helps allow you produce more force which
means you're stronger without getting
any bigger as I mentioned a couple times
already I will do this stuff extensively
in a 55-minute version and walk you
through every piece of it but for now
that's it thanks a lot